I used to spend hours trying to write
the perfect prompts for my AI videos
only to get results that look like this.
But then I realized something. The best
AI videos aren't made using complicated
prompts. They're generated using simple,
clear, intentional prompts that the AI
models actually respond to. So today,
I'm breaking down the only seven prompt
styles you'll ever need. The ones that
work for any AI video.
>> Take cover. The first style prompts are
cinematic prompts. These focus on the
camera work in the scene. It's not just
about what you're seeing, but how you're
observing it. For example, I can have
the static shot of a soldier on a
battlefield. The camera stays perfectly
still, highlighting a moment of peace
and contemplation. And here's a second
shot of that same exact soldier, except
this time we're zooming in and rotating
around to focus in on his face. It's a
much more personal shot.
Other camera movements include panning
to follow our subject as it rolls into
the battlefield. We can use a shaky
handout camera that highlights the
chaotic environment of the soldiers in
the trench getting hit with artillery
shells. Or take that same exact scene
except this time the camera flies above
to a bird's eye view. It's a less
personal and more cold and detached view
of what's going on. Use prompts like the
camera rotates or the camera orbits to
rotate around a subject in a circular
fashion.
There's tons of different camera
movements from camera zooming to camera
pullback, from tilting up to tilting
down, panning left to right, rotations,
and you can also combine different
camera motions together as well. By the
way, the AI videos I'm showing you in
this guide were made using the
imagetovideo technique. First, we give
the AI video generator a reference
image. And then we can enter a prompt
describing how we want the scene to play
out. Here's a image frame of a soldier
in a trench I want to animate. And then
adding a prompt that describes what's
happening inside the scene. So for this
particular shot, I didn't add in any
camera motions. Instead, I just want to
focus on the subject himself of him
pulling a small wooden cross from
underneath his jacket. So with cinematic
prompts, we can control how the camera
is moving throughout the scene. [music]
But what if we want to divide our AI
video into multiple different segments,
each with their own different camera
movements and action happening? That's
where the second prompting method comes
in, which is timestamp prompted. Here's
an 8-second video of an astronaut. In
the first 3 seconds, the camera zooms in
towards him, and then it tilts down to
show him looking at this recording
device. And finally, the camera tilts
back up again to see him looking up
towards the sky. we can actually tell
the AI video generator exactly what
motions to happen along each segment of
the AI video. This will give you a lot
more control over the sequence of events
that are happening and exactly how you
want them to happen. Here's another
example of timestamp prompting [music]
where first I told the camera to zooming
to a over- the-sh shoulder shot of the
astronaut and then end the scene by
zooming in closely on the creature
[music] space. Time stamp prompting is
the best way to organize multiple
actions happening [music] inside a
scene. So, we can divide our AI video
into different segments. But to take
things a step further, we can actually
generate multiple camera angles using
just a single AI video. This video shows
a full body of the astronaut turning and
walking towards a spaceship. But then it
cuts to a close-up shot of his footsteps
along the ground. To create this effect,
I use a third prompt style, which
[music] is the cutscene prompting. For
this particular video, I used the
prompt, "The astronaut turns and walks
towards a spaceship." Cut to the boots
of the astronaut walking along the
terrain inside a [music] cinematic film,
which let me divide this video into two
separate segments. We can combine this
technique with timestamp [music] prompt
to get a huge amount of control over the
direction of the videos. Here's a shot
divided into three segments of an
astronaut on an alien world. We cut to a
close-up shot of his expression of
wonder and awe on his face. And it ends
with a final shot of him exploring the
alien planet. To create this effect,
divide the prompt into different
timestamps. And in each timestamp,
[music]
define a different camera angle or a
different emotion that you want to
happen. This turns AI video generator
into a storyboard tool or video editor.
Time stamp prompting gives you control
over the sequence of events and cutscene
prompting lets you add in different
scenes to tell a full story, turning you
into an AI director. A word of caution
with cutscene prompting. Sometimes if
you prompt for different cuts that are
completely different from the original
video or requires AI video generator to
imagine a lot of new things. So here I
wanted a different cut to inside the
mouth of the plant. it does sometimes
have a hard time maintaining consistency
in the video style. So, it went from a
more realistic style to kind of like a
3D animated scene. So, if you're going
to use cutscene prompting, you want to
make sure that the scene that you're
cutting to isn't too overly different
from what you had in your original shot.
By the way, the prompt techniques I'm
showing work for Google Veo 3, but they
can also be applied to different AI
video models like Sora 2 or Seance or
Cling. Prompt style number four are GPT
prompts. Since we're already creating AI
videos, why not use an AI language model
to help you write the prompts
themselves? I learned this from the AI
video school channel. So, thanks for the
tip. Different AI video models usually
come with their own written guides for
how to prompt inside them. Here's one
for the Google Veil 3 model. And the
documentation includes information like
[music] the best formula for writing
effective prompts and also some
essential prompting techniques. So let's
see what happens if we try teaching an
AI using this information to write
prompts for us. So what I did is I took
that prompt manual and copied over all
the relevant important information like
the formula for writing prompts, uh
prompting techniques, a few examples as
well. And inside chat GPT in the explore
tab, uh, I'm going to go ahead and
create my own GPT. And inside here, what
I did is I gave it a little bit of a job
description. I want this GPT to be a
prompt helper that arrives prompts to
generate AI videos for Google BO 3.1.
Exactly. Um, so I said the user can
enter a description of the scene and you
should generate a prompt for that scene.
And what you'll need to do is actually
upload a PDF file that includes a
documentation of how to write prompts
into the knowledge section. And once
that's done, we have our own GPT prompt
helper. So here's an example where I
uploaded a picture of this woman uh with
this [music] stag. And I told her to
write a prompt for a sad scene where the
female elf is saying goodbye to her old
stag friend. And this is what the GPT
produces for us. So it'll give you a
much longer detailed prompt that
includes all the different elements of
the cinematography, but also to the
sound effects, the style, the lighting,
and all the action that's happening in
the scene. And the video that it
generates [music] more or less captures
what I requested, which was a sad
goodbye scene. It can help reduce the
amount of time you spend typing out the
prompts and instead have this AI helper.
Now, the problem with this is that the
AI is sometimes confused. Here's this
image, and I told it to write a prompt
for a reticent scene as he gets ready to
leave and go on an adventure. Looking at
the prompt GBT gives us, it starts with
a wide morning shot, which doesn't
really make any sense. I think it meant
to say a wide angle shot in the morning.
Now, problems like this are fairly
minor. It's easy to go in and correct
them manually. But the biggest problem
with using this GPT prompt method is in
the AI documentation rarely rarely tells
you what the AI video generator is
[music] bad at. And the difference
between being good at prompting and
being bad at prompting is actually
understanding the limitations of the AI
video, what it can't do. So, if you
train a GPT using information that's
incomplete, that doesn't include what
the AI video generator can't do well,
you're going to have problems that
you're not really sure how to solve.
Here's one example where I chatb to
write a prompt for seeing where the
elven woman is in trouble. The town
spoke have discovered who she is and
they're angry. So, let's [music] just
pretend she's like, you know, a secret
spy or something. And if we go into the
prop, some of the elements that the GPT
asks for include the crowd of angry
towns folks surround her on both sides
shouting and pointing. So something AI
videos can't do well is animating crowds
of people. If you have a lot of people
in the scene and you want them to
perform some actions, it's going to look
really weird. Either they're all going
to do the same thing at the same time,
which happens in Beo 3, or they're just
going to turn to like blobs and blur
together. And of course, the GBT prompt
helper has no way of knowing this since
this is not mentioned in the official
prompt guide from the Google Veil 3
model. And so in the videos, you're
going to get some weird behavior that
doesn't look realistic. Instead, to get
the best results from a scene like this
where there's so many different people,
a better approach that can convey the
same emotion of uneasiness and fear is
to have her looking around nervously
while these people stare at her in
silence in kind of like a weird eerie
way. This will give the same idea across
that she's in hostile territory, but a
prompt like this is much easier for the
AI video to animate. So, I think a GPT
prompt helper like this is very useful
for more advanced users that actually
understand the nuances. But if you're
more of a beginner, I'd really recommend
sticking to simpler, shorter, more
intentional props. So, that way, it's
much easier to go in and figure things
out when they don't work exactly how you
expect it. AI does weird stuff. Things
that seem super obvious to you are not
obvious to the AI at all. For this shot,
I just simply prompted for my character
to be smiling and show a happy
expression. And the AI completely
transforms the way he looks, not knowing
that the ash and red embers covering his
face are actually an important part of
the video. To handle situations like
this, you need prompt style number five,
which is the anchor prompt. We need to
use anchors in the prompts to remind the
AI of [music] what's important to us.
So, if I add in the prompt that there
should be red embers and ash on him,
this time it's actually able to create
the same happy facial expression, but it
keeps the same visual style instead of
transforming him. So, for this prompt, I
anchored in his [music] physical
appearance by saying that he has red
embers and ash on him. Here's another
example of a scene that starts with my
orc character riding on top of the wolf.
But as we progress the scene and the
fight continues, you'll see that he
slides off the wolf in kind of a weird
way. And so to fix that, instead I
modified the prompt to adding the
anchor, reminding the AI in the prompt
that the orc should be on the back
riding the direwolf. And this helps the
AI maintain that relationship between
the two subjects. Sometimes you have to
use anchors to help the AI video
generators understand parts of the scene
that it can't see yet to understand how
to generate parts of the scene later on
that it can't see right now. So I have
this character of an orc and you'll see
on one of his shoulders, his left
shoulders, there's this armor pad and on
his right shoulder there is no armor.
Instead there's this like blue tribal
tattoo. Now, when I try to generate a
video of this specific character from a
styled profile shot that only shows the
left side of his body that has the armor
covering his shoulder, if we watch it,
you'll notice that on his right
shoulder, the armor pad also appears.
And that's because the AI has no way of
knowing based on the initial image frame
of what his other shoulder should
actually look like. And so what I need
to do is adding an anchor to say the orc
has no armor on the right shoulder. Dark
blue geometric tribal tattoos on the
orc's shoulder. Using this anchor, it'll
give the AI a better understanding of
how I want my complete character to
look. So it's not going to be exactly
consistent to the original shot of the
orc because the AI is starting from
nothing. But by anchoring what his full
appearance looks like, we can create a
video where his shoulder looks a lot
more like the original character. To
maximize AI videos capabilities, you got
to use image prompting. To get the most
beautiful shots, like these serialistic
scenes, it's really only possible to do
this consistently if you're using image
prompts. To get this dreamy seralistic
scene of the koi fish flying above a
canal, first I generated an image using
the propped serialism photo, a giant
koiish in the canals of Venice City. And
then I used a clean 2.5 video generator
to animate it into a video. Be direct
and clear in exactly how you want the
scene to unfold. The fish floats
forwards through the air. It's simple,
it's clear, and it's easy for the AI to
understand what I want it to do. A city
floating in the clouds. The lights blink
on and off. Serialism. The giant giraffe
waves in the ocean and eats leaves from
the tree. She blinks. The paper covering
falls off her face to reveal mechanical
gears inside. Image prompting is also
the best way to get multiple shots of a
consistent character inside the scene.
It's the best way to use AI to generate
multiple camera angles. First, I can
start with a front view of my character
sitting inside a plant store. And I can
use an AI image model like Nano Banana
to create a side profile of her studying
at a desk inside of her plant store. Or
I can create a photo of her watering the
plants inside the store. If she gets
tired, she can take a lunch break and
look outside the window to see the
people walking by. With these character
reference photos, we can then use image
prompting to generate multiple shots of
her throughout her day. Whether it's
working, watering her plants, [music]
studying, or taking a lunch break,
there's always incredible new AI image
tools being developed. Here's one I
found called uh Q1 image edit camera
angle control where we can actually
upload an image reference of a character
and use these camera controls to
generate different camera angles of the
same exact scene. So, let's first rotate
it by 45°. And by the way, this is done
completely in real time. As I'm talking,
this is happening. And uh there you see
it rotated, I think, to her left. Um
let's go in the opposite direction.
There it is. There's other options like
zooming in closer to her. You can also
tilt the camera up and down. So bird is
above and worm is below. So let's try
tilting the camera down below her. And
there you have it. If we zoom in on here
a little bit, you'll see that the
textures on her face are kind of smooth.
So, you'll need to use some kind of an
image upscaler to get higher resolution
or like sharper, more realistic details,
but still, this is a pretty incredible
AI image tool for controlling the camera
angles of your scene. With image
prompting, not only can you just use
them as references, you can actually
join them together to control the
beginning and the end of a full shot.
This is called start and end frame
prompting where we can actually use an
image for the first frame of the video
but also use an image to control what's
going on in the last frame of the video.
And then when you combine these things
together, the AI video can actually
render a complete scene of your
character between the two frames. The
seventh prompting style you need to know
is called negative prompting. Sometimes
to get what you want from the AI, it's
actually easier to just tell it what you
don't want to happen. So, I have this
vlog scene of my astronaut on a lunar
colony. Let's say I don't like the way
the moon looks outside the [music]
window. Maybe the perspective just looks
a little bit off and I don't want any
windows on the wall. The easiest way to
handle this is actually just to directly
tell the prompt no windows. [music]
Instead of trying to describe exactly
what the wall should look like and by
using this negative prompt and telling
the AI what I don't want to see inside
the scene, it can generate that same
shot except this time there is no
windows on the wall. Here's a trickier
example where I created this scene of a
soldier and you can hear a bunch of
different gunshots. It's easy to
understand why the AI would use those
sound effects. He is aiming his weapon,
but the result looks a little weird.
There's even like this burst of smoke
coming out from his gas mask. And what I
wanted to create was actually a more
quiet scene of him cautiously observing
his environment. And so I went pretty
heavy with a negative prompt in this
case where I told it to be completely
silent and quiet and no gunshots, no
clicking, no trigger. It sort of worked.
This time you can just hear the flames
in the background without him firing his
weapon. So, you know the different
prompt styles you'll need for AI video.
But there's still so many different cool
AI video tools out there. From lip sync
tools to motion capture. I made a guide
that covers the five levels of AI video
generation that will take you from a
complete beginner to an advanced pro. Go
take a look.